1941年 三人步行 翻越喜瑪拉雅山進入印度
他們歷經4000英哩路途 活著走到自由
謹以本片獻給他們
片名 亡命千萬里 / 回來的路
1939年9月 希特勒從西邊入侵波蘭
幾天後史達林從東邊入侵
他們瓜分了這個國家
不
帶目擊者進來
你認識這人嗎?
認識
他的名字?
亞努思.維斯塞克
目擊者 你跟這人的關係是什麼?
我是他妻子
被告 你能證實這事嗎?
是
目擊者 關於被告你有什麼話要說嗎?
從他談話 我知道了他批評黨...
特別是蘇聯領導人 史達林同志
他們對你做了什麼?
被告 你能證實這些指控嗎?
目擊者 關於被告你還知道什麼?
他為外國勢力當間諜
被告 你能證實這事嗎?
不是
目擊者 你被寬恕了 守衛!
她已經簽署了充分完整的聲明...
詳述你的間諜和陰謀破壞活動
現在你會簽嗎?
你們對她做了什麼?
1940年 西伯利亞
人民的敵人們
你們四處看看就能瞭解...
不是我們的槍 或狗 或鐵絲網 構成你們的監獄
西伯利亞是你們的監獄
它所有面積是500萬平方英哩
大自然是你們的枷鎖 而且它毫不留情
如果大自然沒殺了你...當地人會
有一項恩惠是給每位逃犯的頭的
看那些可憐人
Look at those poor men.
他們得到了夜盲癥
They've got night blindness.
我在過渡集中營見過
I saw it in the transit camp.
因為飢餓缺乏維生素
It's vitamin deficiency from starvation.
這裡 這裡
Here, here.
你計劃用一半的配額生存嗎 孩子?
You planning on surviving on half rations, son?
看 他是個老人
Look, he's an old man.
我也是老人
I'm an old man.
早上我會活著 他不會
I'll be alive in the morning. He won't.
仁慈
Kindness.
在這裡會要了你的命
That can kill you here.
他是美國人
He's American.
在這裡? 怎麼會?
In Here? How?
史達林恨外國人
Stalin hates foreigners,
包括波蘭人
and that includes Poles.
你是波蘭人嗎?
You're Polish, no?
啊哈
我喜歡你們波蘭人
I like you Poles.
你們打抱不平
Your burning sense of injustice,
渴望自由
the yearning for freedom.
卡巴洛夫.安卓.提摩菲耶維屈
Khabarov- Andrei Timofeyevich.
維斯塞克.亞努思
Weiszczek- Janusz.
我能問一下你的罪名嗎 亞努思?
Your charge, may I ask, Janusz?
第58條第10項
58-10.
間諜罪
A spy.
他們是那麼告訴我的
That's what they told me.
10年?
Ten years?
不 20年
No. 20.
第58條第14項 破壞罪 10年
58-14. Sabotage. Ten years.
你在蘇聯邊境
And you were on Soviet side of line,
他們逮捕你 控告你間諜罪
and they arrest you. They accuse you of spying.
折磨你 嗯?
Torture you, huh?
你簽認罪書了嗎?
Did you sign confession?
沒有
No.
沒有 我不簽
No, I wouldn't sign,
所以他們 他們折磨別人
so they-they tortured someone else.
原諒我
Forgive me.
我是位演員
I was actor.
電影
Moving pictures.
上次電影 我演貴族
In my last picture, I played aristocrat.
當影片發佈時他們逮捕我
They arrested me when the film was released.
為什麼?
Why?
它被控訴
it was claimed
我在鼓吹舊貴族地位
I was elevating the status of the old nobility.
所以你因為在影片中表演 而被判刑10年
So you got ten years for a performance in a film.
我的公告好一點
I've had better notices.
不
Nyet.
我繼續賒帳
賒帳? 你已經負債中了
烏爾奇幫
The Urki.
你知道這些人是誰?
Do you know who these are?
職業犯
Professional criminals.
殺人犯和小偷
Murderers and thieves.
別盯他們看
Don't stare at them.
警衛讓他們在這裡圍事
The guards let them run things in here,
而且他們令人害怕
and they are to be feared.
那麼為何他們讓他們圍事?
Then why would they let them run things?
因為他們是中產階級的產物
Because they are byproduct of bourgeois society
和所謂人民的朋友
and so friends of people.
我們是政治犯和所謂人民的敵人
We are political prisoners and so enemies of people.
蘇聯已經變成一個大監獄
The Soviet Union has become one vast prison.
奴役勞工
Slave labor.
他們遠在蘇聯帝國之外
They are from far reaches of Soviet Empire,
全被抓進相同的鐵絲網
all caught up in same net.
啊 他們之中有人設法 逃離這個鐵絲網嗎?
And, uh, do any of them wriggle out of the net?
沒有 亞努思 你必須更小心點
No, Janusz. You must be more careful.
史達林到處有耳目
Stalin has eyes and ears everywhere,
甚至在這裡面
even in here.
如果你不更小心點
If you are not more careful,
一年後你會死
you will die after one year.
即使不是字面上的死
If not literally,
那麼就是心死
then spirit.
你在這裡面多久了?
And how long have you been in here?
11個月又29天
Eleven months and 29 days.
我要這件毛衣
拿這件外套吧
我要毛衣
你祖母做給你的嗎?
你在這裡沒有權力
毛衣
換香腸
你替我畫
You do for me.
你要我畫你?
You want me to draw you?
不 不是我
No. Not me.
當海盜盯著他時 吉姆身體感到一陣顫抖
他全身是傷疤和刺青
而且他只有一條腿
他說"我是隆.約翰.席爾維" (名著金銀島的海盜船長)
我知道一個像那類型的故事 記得伊果嗎? 他有一條腿
閉嘴
繼續講 你會獲得一些麵包的
那麼這位隆.約翰.席爾維如何找到寶藏的?
因此吉姆與這幫窮兇惡極之徒航向金銀島
這些人殺人不眨眼 這些人只愛金子
寄生蟲?
Lice?
吃我為生
Eating me alive.
關於那個 我有祖傳秘方 過來
For that I have old folk remedy. Come.
礦坑
The mine.
他們晚上炸
They blast at night.
你在幹什麼?
What are you doing?
我們必須快點
We must be quick.
否則在早上這個不會在這裡了
Or this will not be here in the morning.
你打算留它在這裡過夜? 為什麼?
You're going to leave it here overnight? Why?
你會知道的
You'll see.
這事做得到的
It can be done.
我知道穿越鐵絲網的辦法
I know a way through the wire.
怎麼穿越?
How?
拉扎爾 我的同伴
Lazar, my associate,
他是建築物的監工
he is overseer of construction.
他指給我看的
He showed me.
如果你曾想逃離這集中營
If you ever escape the camps,
而我一直等待像你這樣的人很久了
and I've been waiting so long for someone like you,
有力量
someone with the strength,
有意志能克服
the will to see it through.
但去哪裡?
But to go where?
我意思是 我們不能往西走
I mean, we can't go west.
我意思是 除了德國人外 就是蘇聯人
I mean, apart from the Germans, there's the Soviets.
而東邊 整個蘇聯直到太平洋
And east, all Soviet right to the Pacific.
不 不 不 不
No, no, no, no.
北邊 必須是... 必須是南邊
North. Have to be- have to be south.
答對了
Correct.
但你知道我們在哪裡嗎? 我意思是 確切位置?
But do you know where we are? I mean, exactly?
我相信我們大約在 貝加爾湖北方500公里地方
I beileve we are about 500 kilometers north of Lake Baikal.
這是湖
This is the lake.
集中營在這裡
Camp is here.
邊境在這裡
And the border is here.
我們可以順著湖這裡的邊緣
We could follow the edge of the lake here.
往南
That runs due south.
正是 然後我們穿越西伯利亞大鐵路
Exactly. Then we cross the Trans-Siberian Railway
到蒙古邊境獲得自由
to the Mongolian border and freedom.
春天已經來了
Spring is already upon us.
我們必須等到秋天
We will have to wait till autumn.
不 為什麼等?
No. Why wait?
為什麼?
Why?
因為到邊境是1000公里 也許更多
Because it is a thousand kilometers to the border, maybe more.
我們需要小心計劃 我們需要屯積食物
We need careful planning. We need to stockpile food.
我已經開始交易 分配
I've already begun trading, dealing.
你必須做一樣的事
You must do the same.
秋天天氣較能預測
And in autumn, the weather is more predictable.
我們可以用新雪掩蓋我們的足跡
We can use the new snow to cover our tracks.
還有我們帶上我的朋友
And we bring my friends.
你的朋友? 你信任他們?
Your friends? You trust them?
當然
Of course.
他們不會全部生存的
They won't all survive.
但他們死時會是自由人
But they will die free men.
自由
Free.
停
看 天氣越來越壞了
我們能怎麼辦?
你決定
我們會凍死的
我們應該回去
對 然後他們會要我腦袋
指揮官 我們即將死在這裡
休息
我們會凍死的
我們死定了
蹲到地上
蹲下
不到一小時我們就會凍死
如果你現在倒斃 我不會有意見的
對 但損失200人...
你們就得解釋一番了
事情可能對你們很糟
蹲到地上
我們可以前進森林找掩蔽
站住
留在你的位置
我會開槍的
那是個真正勇敢的人!
That's a really brave man!
讓犯人在森林裡掩蔽
如果他們跑就射殺他們
首先我們需要大樹枝!
First we need big branches!
一邊一個 然後一個在後面!
One on each side and then one on the back!
幫我 卡濟
Help me, Kazik.
這些放那裡 放在樹枝上
These down there, put it there on the branch.
好 好
Yes, yes.
跟我來 我們都像這樣做
Follow me. We'll both go like this.
什麼?
What?
很好
Good.
對 放那裡
Yes. Put it there.
佐仁! 你的毛毯!
Zoran! Your blanket!
作為防風牆
For a wind break.
進去 來吧
Get in. Come on.
過來!
Come!
請跟我們來! 我們有掩蔽了!
Please come with us! We have shelter!
我是佐仁 南斯拉夫人 那是亞努思
I am Zoran, Yugoslav. That's Janusz.
他是卡濟
And he's Kazik.
侯羅汀斯基
Horodinsky.
他們是波蘭人
They are Polish.
沃斯 我是拉脫維亞人
Voss. I'm Latvian.
國際聯盟啊
It's a League of Nations.
你是?
And you are?
史密斯
Smith.
你的名字
And your first name.
密斯特
Mister.
密斯特.史密斯
Mr. Smith.
沒錯
That's right.
你們不喜歡冷天氣在外面...
你是牛仔嗎?
向前
你也是
不如昨天槍殺我們
Might as well have shot us yesterday.
我們要前往礦坑
We're for the mines.
這些套圈和古埃及人用的一樣
These collars same as used by ancient Egyptian people.
對 但是用在他們的馬 可能吧
Yes, but on their horses, probably.
不 不 不 不 對人也是一樣
No. No, no, no. Same for people.
你怎麼知道?
How do you know?
我是埃及學教授
I was professor of Egyptology,
列寧格勒大學
Leningrad University.
你瘋了嗎? 他們會射殺你的
Are you crazy? They'll shoot you.
我必須離開這裡
I've got to get out of here.
我必須回去
I have to get back.
這可以做到的
It can be done.
什麼可以做到?
What can be done?
他知道穿越鐵絲網的方法
He knows a way through the wire.
他有一個計劃
He has a plan.
噓 誰有計劃?
Shh. Who has a plan?
他的名字叫卡巴洛夫
His name is Khabarov.
演員
The actor.
你認識他嗎?
Do you know him?
他無意逃亡
He has no intention of escaping.
你是什麼意思?
What do you mean?
他是個騙子
He's a liar.
他在這裡幾年了
He's been here for years.
挑出新到者
Seeks out new arrivals.
我 當我剛到這裡
Me, when I first came here.
他只是喜歡談論逃亡
He just likes to talk about escape.
我認識像他一樣的其他人
I've known others like him.
我為何要相信你?
Why should I believe you?
在集中營裡沒有無緣無故的事情
Nothing is for nothing in the camps.
從你身上他獲得你的能量 你的精神
From you he gets your energy, your spirit.
你供給了他逃亡的夢想
You feed his dream of escape.
你幫忙讓他活著
You help keep him alive.
他只是個吸血鬼
He's nothing but a leech.
你是個冷血的討厭鬼 密斯特
You are a cold bastard, Mister.
我依然活著 就我所知
I'm still alive, that's all I know.
但我不會還要6個月
But I won't be in another six months,
你也不會 不是在這裡
and neither will you. Not here.
不是在這些礦坑裡面
Not in these mines.
但如果你是認真的...
But if you are serious-
關於逃走真的認真的話...
really serious about making a run for it-
我跟著你
I'm with you.
我以為你是個獨行俠
I thought you were a loner.
獨自一人是無法辦到的
It can't be done alone.
而且 你有個弱點
Besides, you have a-a weakness.
你對我可能有用
You could be useful to me.
那是什麼?
And what is that?
仁慈
Kindness.
如果我發生了什麼事
If anything happens to me,
我得靠你背我
I'm counting on you carrying me.
卡巴洛夫
Khabarov.
卡巴洛夫 過來
Khabarov, come.
什麼?
What?
跟我來 現在
Come with me. Now.
是什麼事? 怎麼? 怎麼?
What is it? What? What?
來 看這個
Come. Look at this.
看這個
Look at this.
我們可以走了 我們今晚可以走了
We can go. We can go tonight.
暴風雪會掩蓋我們的足跡
The storm will cover our tracks.
不 不 不 你在說什麼? 它是個過境暴風雪!
No, no, no. What are you talking about? It's a passing storm!
不 這樣就夠了
No, it's enough.
亞努思 那是不可能的
Janusz, that is impossible.
我們需要...我們需要周詳的準備
We need- We need detailed preparation,
我們需要計劃 我們需要地圖
we need plans, we need maps.
不 不 時機永遠不會完美的
No, no, the timing will never be perfect.
看 他們現在沒有預期到暴風雪
Look, they won't expect it now.
你瘋了嗎?
Are you crazy?
距離呢?
What about the distances, huh?
它是...它是1000公里 並且我們需要食物
It's, it's a thousand kilometers, and we need food.
大量的食物
Plenty of food.
但是...但是我們有食物 你有食物
But, but we have food. You have food.
注意 美國人跟我們一起
Look, the American is with us.
我們一直在交易 就像你說的
We've been trading, just like you said.
那能持續多久?
How long will that last?
注意 我已經花費半生
Look, I've spent half my life
在森林和山裡
In the woods and mountains.
離開這地方我們可以活下去
We can live off the land.
你不明白 你太年輕
You don't understand. You are too young.
這事是辦不到的
It cannot be done.
還有什麼?
What else is there?
你聽到我說的嗎?
You hear me?
待在這裡然後死?
To stay here and die?
這事是辦不到的
It cannot be done.
安卓! 我們要如何穿越鐵絲網?
Andrei! How do we get through that wire?
我不知道你在說什麼
I don't know what you are talking about.
你的朋友拉扎爾...
Your friend Lazar-
我意思是 他知道不是嗎?
I mean, he knows, doesn't he?
是你告訴我的
You told me that.
馬上離開
Piss off now.
你看不見對吧?
You can't see, can you?
拜託不要丟下我
Please don't leave me behind.
答應我 安德瑞斯
Promise me, Andrejs.
晚上我可以抓住你的肩膀
I can hold onto your shoulder by night.
我可以 我可以看見形狀
I can-I can see shapes.
白天我可以剛剛好看見
By day I can see just fine.
我不會阻礙你的
I won't hold you up.
拜託不要告訴其他人
Please don't tell the others.
在這裡面我會死
In here, I die.
瑞士的
Swiss.
金錶
首先你必須停止發電機
燈光會暗下來 可能只有10分鐘
那是你的機會
你必須等到最後的哨兵換班
這裡沒有秘密
There are no secrets here.
你要做什麼?
What do you want?
遊戲我輸了
The game goes against me.
小債 他們剁手指
Small debt, they take fingers.
大債 他們砍頭
Big debt, they take head.
我 大債
Me, big debt.
但我永遠不會賭我的狼
But I never gambie my Wolf.
在森林裡 你需要刀子
In forest, you need knife,
而我需要奇? 帶我離開這裡
and I need miracle. Get me out of here.
他們砍斷了柱子
我看不見
那裡! 鐵絲網被剪斷了
放狗
來吧! 來吧!
Come on! Come on!
小心! 繼續走 繼續走!
Look! keep going. Keep going!
我們必須繼續走! 起來!
We must keep going! Get up!
起來!
Get up!
動起來 否則我們馬上會死
Activity, or we die right now.
你知道狗跑得多快
You know how fast the dogs are.
跑啊 該死!
Run, damn you!
密斯特 來啊 看著我
Mister, come on, look at me.
到了我背你的時候嗎?
Is it time for me to carry you?
來吧 來吧
Come on. Come on.
來吧!
Come on!
亞努思 我們看不見東西!
Janusz, we can't see anything!
雪讓我們看不見!
The snow is blinding us!
亞努思!
Janusz!
我需要你的刀!
I need your knife!
給我刀子!
Give me the knife!
你的刀!
Your knife!
亞努思 我們必須找掩蔽!
Janusz, we must take shelter!
我們無法繼續下去!
We can't go on!
你不明白嗎? 這太完美了!
Don't you see? This is perfect!
像這樣他們永遠不會發現我們
They'll never find us like this.
永遠不會!
Never!
你盯著我像是蛇盯著兔子
You stare at me like snake at rabbit.
他教我英語
He teach me English.
說得很好吧?
Speak good, huh?
麵包換語言 不是嗎 牛仔?
Bread for words, wasn't it, cowboy?
我們已經來到多遠?
How far have we come?
也許20 30公里
Maybe 20, 30 kilometers.
就那樣?
That's all?
更少 如果我們一直繞圈子的話
Less, if we've been going in circles
像無頭雞一樣
like chicken without head.
好吧 我們看看有什麼
All right, let's see what we have.
每個人 來吧
Everyone, come on.
我們分享所有東西
We share everything.
你呢?
And you?
怎樣?
What?
你有嗎?
Do you have?
那件外套
And that coat.
它不是你的外套
It's not your coat.
那是卡巴洛夫的外套
That is Khabarov's coat.
對 他給我的
Yes, he gave me.
還有...
And...
嗯? 嗯?
看見了嗎?
See?
他要去告發
He was going to inform.
別擔心 我跟他說了
Don't worry. I talk to him.
一切沒事
Everything okay.
你和魔鬼做了交易
You've made a bargain with the devil.
你瞭解嗎?
You realize that?
你有刀嗎?
Do you have a knife?
他用草和苔蘚辨認方向 那是什麼?
For direction he uses grass and the mosses. What's that?
我向上帝發誓 他最好知道他在幹嘛
I swear to God he better know what he's doing.
你應該感激 你畢竟在這裡
You should be grateful you're here at all.
感激是給狗的
Grateful is for dogs.
是什麼... 那是什麼?
What- What's that?
狼 只是狼而已
Woives. It's only wolves.
只是狼而已
Only wolves.
南邊
South.
到貝加爾湖
To Lake Baikal.
你是"帕坎"
You are the Pakhan.
是嗎?
Am I?
什麼是帕坎?
What is a Pakhan?
烏爾奇幫的老大
Boss of Urki.
我們不是罪犯
We are not criminals.
我們脫離了罪犯
We are escaping from criminals.
我一直在注視你
I have been watching you.
我向上帝發誓 你贏得我的尊敬
And I swear to God you win my respect
包括你的手杖和松果
with your sticks and pine cones.
在你面臨生死之際 我會為你挺身而出
I'll come between you and death.
所以你想當我的保鑣?
So you want to be my bodyguard?
這是Urka的方式
It's the Urka way.
你有我 而且你有這隻狼
You have me, and you have the Wolf.
嗯?
亞努思 我們到達湖要多久?
Janusz, how long till we get to the lake?
多久?
How long?
三 四個星期
Three, four weeks.
也許更多
Maybe more.
我猜我們在這裡某處
I have us here somewhere.
下去這裡 西伯利亞大鐵路
And down here, the Trans-Siberian Railway,
然後蒙古邊境
and the border of Mongolia.
蒙古似乎很遠
Mongolia seems so far away.
蒙古? 我走更遠
Mongolia? I go more.
到美國
To America.
就像這個... 我們下周有食物
It's like this- we have food for another week.
我們沒有火柴了
We have no more matches.
但我們仍然有卡巴洛夫的打火石
But still we have Khabarov's flint.
我們需要肉
We need meat.
我會做陷阱
I can make traps.
我們移動太快 等不及陷阱
We'll be moving too fast to wait for traps.
我們找農場 村莊那裡取得食物
We find farms, villages, get food there.
看 有項恩惠在我們頭上 記得嗎
Look, there's a bounty on our heads. Remember that.
我們晚上偷 他們永遠不會知道
We steal it. At night. They never know.
我們不是小偷
We are not thieves.
那麼我會偷 而且我會吃
Then I'll steal it, and I'll eat.
你可以看
You can watch.
那是什麼?
What is that?
帶刺鐵絲網
Barbed wire.
他在做魚鉤
He's making a fish-hook.
那就是我們如何生存的方法了
That's how we will survive.
吃魚?
With fish?
啊
但我不吃魚
But I don't eat fish.
那麼你會死
Then you'll die.
來吧
Come on,
我們需要生火
we need to make a fire.
來吧 要很多木材
Come on, lots of wood.
今晚會在零下40度
It'll be 40 below tonight.
托馬斯?
Tomasz?
不 不 不要太多 不要太多
No, no, not too much, not too much.
卡濟?
Kazik?
他仍然在外面找木材
He's still out, looking for wood.
他有夜盲癥
He has night blindness.
卡濟!
Kazik!
亞努思!
Janusz!
教授
Professor.
我從礦坑來找你
I came from the mine to find you.
我以為我是獨自一人
I thought I was alone.
我一直跟著你走了一些時間了
I've been walking with you for some time.
我...我只是坐一會兒
I'll- I'll just sit for a minute.
不遠了
Not far to go.
我們做到了
We made it.
我們真的做到了
We really made it.
那不是很了不起嗎?
Isn't that something?
上帝 安息這個無辜的靈魂吧
Lord, take this innocent soul into thy keeping.
阿門
Amen.
今天一位自由人死在這裡
A free man died here today.
此外 少了一張嘴要養
Still, one less mouth to feed.
怎麼?
What?
他們會發現我們的骨頭和你的畫
They'll find our bones and your drawings
今後100年
a hundred years from now
然後說"看 早先古拉格集中營的很好例子"
and say "Look, a fine example of Early Gulag Man. "
閉上你的玩笑
Shut up with your jokes.
像其他人一樣去找食物
Go and find food like the others do.
你才要閉嘴!
You do the shutting up!
整天畫畫 好像你在過節日
Drawing all day like you're on holiday.
我生病了
I'm sick.
我煮東西 他們找食物
I cook. They find food.
你做過什麼?
What do you ever do?
沒有
Nothing.
但我讓你笑開懷
But I make you all laugh.
不 不再是了 你沒有
No, not anymore, you don't.
那麼...
So...
誰會是第一個?
who will be first?
你是什麼意思 第一個?
What do you mean, first?
第一個死
The first to die.
我想是藝術家
I think the artist.
但如果是他更好 這個搞笑人
But better if it was him, the funny man.
為何最好是佐仁?
Why better if it's Zoran?
較軟
More soft.
較...嫩
More-tender.
密斯特現在只能抓很少的魚
Mister only catch little fish now.
我們必須吃肉 否則我們會死在這裡
We must have meat, or we die here.
你是帕坎 你思考過了
You're the Pakhan, you've thought of it.
我們全都思考過了
We all have.
那就是為何你帶額外的人 不是嗎?
That's why you brought extra people, isn't it?
為了食物?
For food?
不 不 不
No, no, no.
我們會得到更多的食物 當我們到達貝加爾湖時
We will get more food when we get to Lake Baikal.
那裡會有很多魚
There will be plenty of fish there.
你一周前說我們會看見湖
You said we would have seen lake a week ago.
嗯?
我們迷路了 帕坎
We're lost, Pakhan.
啊!
呀!
呀! 呀!
注意 如果我 啊 如果我找到湖
Look, if I, uh, if I find the lake,
一周內我會回來
I will be back in a week.
如果我沒回來 那麼就看你們自己了
If I don't, well, you're on your own.
我知道
I know.
我們的朋友瓦卡
Our friend Valka.
別讓他脫離你的視線
Don't let him out of your sight.
給你
Here.
今天早上新鮮的
Fresh this morning.
謝謝
Thank you.
祝好運
Good luck.
你也是
And you.
亞努思!
Janusz!
我看到它了 我看到它了
I saw it. I saw it.
我看到湖了
I saw the Lake.
放鬆 放鬆
Easy, easy.
距離這裡三天
Three days from here.
石頭! 收集石頭!
Stones! Gather stones!
把它們用火加熱!
Heat them in the fire!
怎麼了?
What is it?
噓 噓
噓 嘿
Hey.
有人一直在跟我們
Someone's been following us.
他在那簇漆黑的森林後面
He's behind that dark clump of trees.
如果他告發我們
If he gives us away,
他們會立即遍佈我們周圍
they'll be all over us in no time.
他說得對 我們必須這麼做
He's right. We have to do this.
不能殺人
No killing.
不能?
No?
我想你之前已經殺過人
I think you've killed before.
你為無辜的人說太多禱告了
You say too many prayers for an innocent man.
瓦卡 你走後面
Valka, you go behind
以防他跑去告發 去
in case he makes a run for it. Go.
散開 散開
Spread out, spread out.
瓦卡 不要
Valka, no.
不要!
No!
我們...我們不會傷害你
We-we won't hurt you.
嗯
波蘭婦女
A Polka.
波蘭婦女? 她要幹嘛?
Polka? What does he want?
我不知道 是個女孩
I don't know. It's a girl.
而且她是波蘭人
And she's Polish.
她一直跟著我們好幾天了
She's been following us for several days.
然後怎樣?
And what?
嗯 她需要食物 你知道 保護
Well, she needs food, you know, protection.
她一直太害怕接近我們
She's been too afraid to approach us
直到她確認我們不是蘇聯人
until she was sure we weren't Russian.
她想跟我們一起旅行嗎?
She wants to travel with us?
她在逃亡 像我們一樣
She's on the run, like us.
她會拖慢我們速度
She'll slow us down.
她說她逃離
She said she's escaped
從一個蘇聯集中農場
from a Russian collective farm.
我知道這類型...街頭吉普賽
I know this type- street gypsies.
有好幾千個像那樣的人 比一條狗還沒用!
There are thousands like that, less use than a dog!
帕坎 別這麼做 嗯?
Pakhan, don't do this?
噢 拜託 她餓死了
Oh, come on. She's starving.
我幾乎無法養我們自己
We can barely feed ourselves.
對 也許丟下她比較好
Yeah, maybe it's kinder to leave her.
不 她被送到我們這裡 我們不能丟下她
No, she was sent to us. We can't leave her.
亞努思 我們沒有選擇
Janusz, we have no choice.
嘿 嘿 嘿 嘿!
Hey, hey, hey, hey!
嘿! 嘿 嘿 嘿 嘿!
Hey! Hey, hey, hey, hey!
後退
Stay back.
後退 小心泥漿
Stay back. Careful of the mud.
慢慢來 慢慢來 慢慢來
Easy. Easy. Easy.
瓦卡
Valka.
給你的
Here you are.
找些木材
Find some wood.
她名字叫艾琳娜
Her name is Irena.
肥皂準備好了嗎?
Is the soap ready?
對
Yes.
啊 很好
Ah, good.
攪拌
Stir.
那個?
Well?
什麼事那麼好笑?
What's so funny?
你...
Are you-
你今天早上要去辦公室嗎?
you are going to the office this morning?
瓦卡?
Valka?
瓦卡
Valka.
來吧
Come on.
你是下一個 去 去
You're next. Go, go.
瓦卡 來吧!
Valka, come on!
現在脫掉你的襯衫
Now take off your shirt.
我們為何做這事?
Why do we do this?
那麼我們不會看起來 像是小偷和強盜
So we don't look like thieves and robbers.
頭抬起來
Head up.
現在別動
Now, still.
千萬別動 拜託
Very still, please.
頭抬起來
Head up.
再抬高一點
More.
不
Nyet.
你知道嗎 我啊 不相信她是波蘭人
You know, I, uh, can't beiieve she's Polish.
她啊 她受過教育
She's, uh, she's educated.
會說流利英語 法語
Speaks good English, French.
那樣對嗎?
Is that right?
你不喜歡她嗎?
You don't like her, do you?
跟瓦卡談到她
Speak to Valka about her.
他甚至不認為她是波蘭人
He doesn't even think she's Polish.
嗯 我的確和他談過
Well, I did speak to him.
還有其他人
And the others.
他們都贊成她跟我們一起來
They agree she comes with us.
怎麼 你不贊成?
What, you disagree?
沒有多愁善感的餘地了 你知道的
There's no room for sentimentality, you know that.
撇開食物不說 她會拖慢我們的速度
Apart from food, she'll slow us down.
不 它無法承擔我們的重量
No, it won't take our weight.
我們必須游泳過去
We'll have to swim across.
你會游嗎?
Can you swim?
會 密斯特
Yes, Mister.
你不會騙我吧
You wouldn't lie to me.
我沒說謊 同志
I'm not lying, Comrade.
別叫我同志
And don't call me Comrade.
艾琳娜 不要!
Irena, no!
這裡 來吧
Here, come on.
這裡 拿著食物
Here, take the food.
你父母和你一起被逮捕嗎?
Were your parents arrested with you?
他們死了
They're dead.
我們住在華沙外的農場
We lived on a farm outside Warsaw.
當蘇聯人來時
When the Russians came,
他們說我們是富農
they said we were kulaks
而且剝削農人
and exploiting the peasants.
我父母害怕並把我藏在穀倉內
My parents were afraid and hid me in the barn.
我之後發現他們
I found them later.
我...
I-
我發現他們臉部向下倒在泥漿中
I found them face-down in the mud.
他們被毆打並被帶刺的鐵絲網勒死
They'd been bashed and strangled with barbed wire.
之後 蘇聯人抓到我
Later, the Russians caught me
然後送我去一個集中農場
and sent me to a collective farm.
他們對我很殘酷
They were cruel to me.
我逃離了
I ran away.
我沒有食物
I had no food.
然後我看到你們
And then I saw you.
你不會游泳嗎?
You can't swim, can you?
什麼?
What?
你一生中從未接近過水
You've never been near the water in your life.
但我過去了不是嗎? 而且你跟隨
But I got across, didn't I? And you followed.
你說你住在靠近華沙的一個農場?
And you said you lived on a farm near Warsaw?
對
Yes.
蘇聯不會到那麼遠
Soviets didn't get that far.
那是德國領土
That was German territory.
你父母沒被殺害對吧?
Your parents weren't murdered, were they?
你虛構了所有的事
You made all that up.
我們可都做了可怕的事以求生存
We've all done terrible things to survives.
因此不要再對我說謊
But don't ever lie to me again.
我們已經受夠了謊話
We've had enough of lies.
我們必須繞過去
We have to go around it.
快點通過它
Quicker through it.
不 他們有狗
No, they have dogs.
如果他們鳴警鈴 那麼我們就沒希望了
If they raise the alarm, then we don't stand a chance.
我們再度需要食物 帕坎
We need food again, Pakhan.
看好 我知道我們需要食物
Look, I know we need food,
但我們不能走進那個鎮冒險被捕
but we can't go into that town and risk arrest.
我們在浪費時間
We're wasting time.
怎麼了? 什麼問題?
What is it? What's wrong?
瓦卡在哪裡?
Where's Valka?
他在佐仁後面
He was behind Zoran.
佐仁 你沒看著他嗎?
Zoran, weren't you watching him?
我不是他的監護人
I'm not his keeper.
該死的他
Damn him.
他可能為了獎賞改變了我們命運
He could turn us in for the bounty.
還有冒險被捕?
And risk arrest?
他是個賭徒
He's a gambler.
艾琳娜 你想他會那麼做嗎?
Irena, do you think he would do that?
他可能會
He might.
我們不需要他的刀子
We don't need his knife.
我們可以從鹿的骨頭做一個
We can make one out of deer bone.
這是個擺脫他的機會
It's an opportunity to get rid of him.
好吧 好吧
All right, all right.
來吧 我們走
Come on, let's go.
當心點好笑的人?
Watch it funny man?
嘿 嘿 嘿!
Hey, hey, hey!
你想讓我們都被殺嗎? 嗯?
You want to get us all killed? Hmm?
嗯?
放輕鬆 牛仔
Easy, cowboy.
你撕破我的外套
You tear my coat.
白癡
Idiot.
白癡? 哈
Idlot? Ha.
是我嗎?
Am I?
我們看誰是白癡
Let's see who is idiot.
怎麼?
What?
我殺了?
Did I kill?
對
Yes.
一隻狗
A dog.
不相信我就不要吃
Don't believe me, then don't eat.
但你們會吃的不是嗎 因為你們想生存
But you will, won't you, because you want to survive.
我一輩子都知道生存
I know about survive.
All my life.
還有...
And-
今天是我的生日
it's my birthday.
在蘇聯 那意謂我們要喝酒
In Russia, that means we drink.
她住在街上 像我一樣
She lived in the streets, like me.
所以你告訴我們的故事不是真的
So the story you told us wasn't true.
我以為那故事會比較悲傷
I thought that story would be more sad
你們不會把我丟下不管
and you wouldn't leave me behind.
我父母是波蘭共產黨員
My parents were Polish Communists.
他們帶我們住在蘇聯莫斯科
They took us to live in Soviet Union, to Moscow.
他們想從事革命
They want to work for the Revolution.
我們住在盧克斯旅館
We lived in the Hotel Lux,
和許多外國共產黨員一起
with lots of foreign Communists.
但他們在1937年逮捕他們
But they arrested them in 1937.
他們說他們是間諜
They said they were spies.
他們的人在孤兒院抓到我
The people pot me in the orphanage.
和我弟弟
And my brother,
他死了
he died.
我當時10歲
I was ten years old.
他們叫我莉可
They called me Rykov,
但我記得我們的波蘭名字...吉琳斯卡
but I remembered our Polish name- Zielinska.
每晚我睡覺前習慣說這名字
I used to say it every night before I went to sleep.
所以你逃跑了
So you ran away.
喔
他們沒蚊子
They have no mosquitoes.
我們能怎麼做?
What can we do?
偷艘船?
Steal a boat?
不 太冒險了
No, it's too risky.
我們的人快要得病了
People are going to get ill.
我知道
I know.
那不是很怪嗎?
Isn't it strange?
我們遭遇所有事之後
After all we've faced,
這些小蟲可能擊倒我們
these tiny insects might bring us down.
在那裡又一次
There it is again.
沒蚊子!
No mosquitoes!
佐仁! 佐仁!
Zoran! Zoran!
他在幹嘛 拜託?
What's he doing, for God's sake?
驅蚊器
Mosquito repellent.
那麼你對他說了什麼?
So what you say to him?
誰?
Who?
蚊子先生
The mosquito man.
啊
我是個逃犯
I'm an escaped convict
飽受蚊子折磨
who is plagued by mosquitoes.
是啊 非常好笑
Yeah, very funny.
不 說真的 你說了什麼?
No, really, what did you say?
來吧 兄弟
Come on, man.
小丑
Clown.
再見 貝加爾湖
Goodbye, Lake Baikal.
做得好
Well done.
密斯特 你知道沃斯是個牧師嗎?
Mister, did you know Voss is a priest?
不 我不知道
No, I didn't know that.
還有托馬斯是糕餅廚師
And Tomasz is a pastry chef,
但他想當藝術家
but he wants to be an artist.
你沒說
You don't say.
還有佐仁在莫斯科做生意
And Zoran was on business in Moscow,
在紅場被逮捕
arrested in Red Square.
他說他只是拍張克里姆林宮的相片
He said he was just taking a photo of the Kremlin.
他是位會計師
He's an accountant.
那麼 我會被罵死的
Well, I'll be damned.
我從不知道一位有趣的會計師
I never knew a funny accountant.
你沒有彼此交談嗎?
Don't you talk to each other?
在集中營裡你學會盡可能少說話
In the camps you learn to say as little as possible.
史密斯先生?
Mr. Smith?
在莫斯科地下鐵工作?
Working on the Moscow Metro?
他是位工程師
He's an engineer.
他父親是芬蘭人
His father was Finnish.
在美國長大 但他會說俄語
Grew up in America, but he could speak Russian.
為何一個美國人會搬到蘇聯 拜託?
And why would an American move to Russia, for God's sake?
因為意志消沉
The Depression.
他兒子跟著他
His son came with him.
他兒子怎麼了?
What happened to his son?
他們射殺了他
They shot him.
他當時17歲
He was 17.
蒙古邊境
The Mongolian border
位於那些鐵軌的另一邊
is on the other side of those tracks-
也許四 五天之遠
maybe four, five days away.
我們能從其他地方穿越嗎?
Can we cross somewhere else?
這裡 這是主幹道
Here, this is the main line.
每個地方都會像這個一樣
It's going to be like this everywhere.
他說的對 我們等到晚上
He's right. We wait till tonight.
怎麼?
What?
沒事 只是在看
Nothing. just looking.
別看
Don't look.
瓦卡?
Valka?
怎麼?
What?
在你胸部為何有混蛋的刺青呢?
Why do you have assholes tattooed on your chest?
我意思是 他們應該在你屁股上
I mean, they should be on your ass
每次你大便時 你就坐在他們上面
so you can sit on them every time you take a shit.
你認為很好笑嗎?
You think it's funny?
他們是偉人
They are great men.
哇 哇! 瓦卡! 瓦卡!
Whoa, whoa! Valka! Valka!
你不知道"史達林"的意思嗎 搞笑人?
Don't you know what "Stalin" means, funny man?
意思是鋼鐵人
Means Man-of-Steel.
他劫富濟貧
He takes from rich and gives to poor.
對 當然他是
Yes, of course he does.
然後他兩者都拿
Then he takes both of them
並把他們關進古拉格集中營25年
and puts them in a Gulag for 25 years.
小心你的眼睛 (挖去當)烏鴉的誘餌
Watch your eyes, crow bait.
謝謝你的盛情款待 蘇聯母親
Thank you, Mother Russia, for your hospitality,
但我絕對不會回來
but I will definitely not be coming back.
你知道他們...他們會抓你
You know, they'll- they'll catch you.
是啊 坐牢還好
Yeah. Prison is okay.
債務不好
Debt is bad.
然而有許多的監獄
But there are many prisons,
他們找不到我
they don't find me.
美國怎麼辦?
What about America?
哦 它不適合我 自由
Oh. It's not for me, freedom.
我不知道怎麼面對 我發誓
I wouldn't know what to do with it, I swear to God.
所以我們必須說再見了 我的狼和我
So we must say goodbye, my Wolf and me.
你不再需要他了
You don't need him anymore.
祝好運 瓦卡
Good luck, Valka.
再見 亞努思
Goodbye, Janusz.
注意 看到了嗎?
Look. See?
你想我們晚上會到那裡嗎?
Do you think we'll get there by tonight?
會 我是這麼想的
Yes, I think so.
我們會做什麼?
What will we do?
我們會吃
We will eat.
好
Yes.
我們會睡
We will sleep.
我們做到了
We made it.
密斯特!
Mister!
他們是共產黨員
They're communists.
所以這裡也一樣了
So it's here too.
這改變了所有事
This changes everything.
無處可躲
There's nowhere to hide.
它是個佛教廟宇
It's a Buddhist temple.
他們可能接納我們
They might take us in.
他們也可能和政權一起工作
They might also be working with the regime.
這是個賭注
It's a risk.
這裡發生什麼事了?
What happened here?
和在蘇聯發生的事一樣
The same as happened in Russia.
教會關閉...
Churches closed...
牧師被槍殺或抓去集中營...
priests shot or taken to camps...
宗教禁止
religion banned.
他們來到我在拉脫維亞的教會
They came to my church, in Latvia.
毀損每樣東西 很像這座廟宇
Destroyed everything, much like this.
之後那晚我回去了
I went back later that night,
有一個孤獨...孤獨的守衛
and there was a lone- lone guard.
只是一個男孩
Just a boy.
然後我勒死他
And I strangled him
直到他的眼睛爆出他的頭
until his eyes popped right out of his head.
不知瓦卡怎麼知道的
Valka knew somehow.
他知道我冷血殺人
He knew I'd killed in cold blood.
中國距離多遠?
How far is China?
我不知道
I don't know.
也許往南五 六百公里
Maybe five, six hundred kilometers due south.
六百公里?
600 kilometers?
中國自由嗎?
Is Chlna free?
他們正在對抗日本人
They're fighting the Japs.
我只知道那麼多
I know that much.
中國之後是西藏
After China is Tibet.
我們可以去首都拉薩
We could go to Lhasa, the capital.
什麼? 你在說什麼?
What? What are you talking about?
他們說我們可以經過西藏
They say we could go beyond Tibet,
越過高山到印度
over the mountains to India.
什麼山?
What mountains?
喜馬拉雅山
The Himalayas.
加入英國部隊
Join the British Army.
對抗納粹 然後對抗蘇聯
Fight Nazls, then fight the Russians.
越過喜馬拉雅山?
Go over the Himalayas?
怎麼過? 坐魔毯嗎?
How? On a magic carpet?
怎麼過?
How?
我們走路
We walk.
小心
Careful.
來吧 起床
Come on, wake up.
我正好美夢之中
I was in the middle of this beautiful dream.
我正要吃些鹽
I was about to eat some salt.
我幾乎?到了
I almost taste it.
我只是想回去那個夢裡
I just want to go back to that dream.
這是非常簡單的食譜
It's a very simple recipe.
你只需要兩根迷迭香
You just need two sprigs of rosemary
和一撮肉豆蔻
and a pinch of nutmeg.
肉豆蔻? 鹽怎麼辦?
Nutmeg? What about the salt?
不 我們會...我們會說到的 現在...
No, we'll-we'll get to that. Now-
加點油...
add the oil-
嗯嗯
然後你將它放進去醃
and you leave it to marinate
當你的雞準備好時
while you prepare the chicken.
這地方放鹽進來
This is where the salt comes in.
很好
Good.
你把它抹在雞的表皮上
You rub it into the skin of the chicken
加點辣椒粉
with a little bit of the paprika.
但是雙倍的鹽
But double the salt.
注意 你不能只放雙倍的鹽
Look, you cannot just doubie the sait.
那樣會太咸了
It'll be too salty then.
我不在乎 就放雙倍的鹽
I don't care, just doubie the sait.
我不打算破壞它
I'm not going to ruin it.
放雙倍的鹽就好 拜託
just double the salt, please.
不行
No.
托馬斯...
Tomasz-
不行
No.
好了 好了 大家保持安靜
All right, all right. Everybody keep calm.
噢 我的天!
Oh, my God!
不 不 不! 別跑! 別跑
No, no, no! Don't run! Don't run.
保持鎮定和微笑 很友善的
Be calm and smile. Be friendly.
嘿 喔! 喔!
Hey, whoa! Whoa!
大家微笑
Everybody smile.
哈羅 哈羅
Hello. Hello.
蘇聯人
不 美國人
你去拉薩嗎?
拉薩 對 西藏
朝聖
對
沒馬嗎?
我們太窮了沒馬
妻子?
不 女兒
有水嗎?
那是南方
That's south.
我們打算吃那個嗎?
Are we going to eat that?
要嘛這個 或是魚
It's either this or fish.
看起來像是鳥巢
It looks like a bird's nest.
它能為你遮蔽陽光
It will protect you from the sun.
艾琳娜 試試你的腳
Irena, try this for your feet.
南方
South.
來吧 我們繼續走
Come on, we keep going.
不 它是另一個海市蜃樓
No, it's another mirage.
我們沒有水
We have no water.
那裡有樹
There's trees there.
如果有樹 就有水
If there's trees, there-there's water.
不 我不在乎
No, I don't care.
那是東方 我們要往南
It's east. We're going south.
但是 亞努思 我們必須試一下
But, Janusz, we've got to give it a try.
不 不 不 我們必須繼續往南
No, no, no. We must keep going south,
否則你殺了我們全部人
or you'll kill us all.
該死!
Damn it!
亞努思 我們快死了
Janusz, we're dying.
我們已經要死了
We're already dying.
停
Stop.
它是個海市蜃樓!
It's a mirage!
它只是個海市蜃樓
It's just a mirage.
海市蜃樓沒有鳥
Mirages don't have birds.
海市蜃樓沒有鳥!
Mirages don't have birds!
那是口井!
It's a well!
別喝太多 你會生病的
Don't fill yourselves. You'll get sick.
至少這裡我們有水
At least we have water here.
噓 噓 你會吵醒她
Shh. Shh. You'll wake her.
是啊 但是沒食物
Yeah, but no food.
也許遊牧民族會帶他們的牲畜來喝水
Maybe nomads will come to water their flocks.
什麼時候?
When?
下周 下月?
Next week, next month?
我們應該待這裡至少幾天
We should stay here at least a few more days.
注意聽好 沒有食物 我們只會越來越虛弱
Look, without food, we'll only get weaker.
然後也許太虛弱了無法旅行
And then maybe too weak to travel.
我不知道 經歷過去幾天之後...
I don't know. After these last days-
我不知道我是否能再經歷一次
I don't know if I can go through that again.
找到這口井是個奇?
It was a miracle finding this.
我們能寄望另一個嗎?
Can we count on another?
亞努思?
Janusz?
好 盡你所能給我倒
Okay, give me your best.
哦!
啊 哈 哈!
等 等 等!
Wait, wait, wait!
開始 托馬斯!
Go, Tomasz!
請摘下帽子
Hat, please.
低一點
Lower.
跑! 跑!
Run! Run!
回頭 回頭! 找掩蔽!
Get back, get back! Take cover!
躲在那沙丘後面!
Behind that dune!
艾琳娜! 趴下!
Irena! Get down!
別害怕!
Don't be afraid!
艾琳娜
Irena.
曬乾的魚
Sun-dried fish.
謝謝
Thank you.
給你
Here.
你能找到我們回井的路嗎?
Can you find our way back to the well?
當然不行
It was way off course.
記得嗎? 我意思是 東邊方向
Remember? I mean, way east.
沒有...
There's no-
這片荒土沒有特徵
There's no features in this wasteland.
我可能永遠找不到
I could never find it.
當我在農田里幫我爸爸
When I helped my father in the fields
在嚴熱夏天期間
during the hot summers,
我們習慣含這樣的小石頭
we used to suck on small stones like these.
讓我們感覺比較不渴
Made us feel less thirsty.
亞努思!
Janusz!
中暑?
Sunstroke?
我快變成討厭的人了
I'm becoming a nuisance.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
他們有傷害你嗎?
Do they hurt you?
沒有 一點也沒有
No, not at all.
它們一定腫起來了 因為我已經走太遠了
They must be swelling because I've walked so far.
你不認為嗎 密斯特?
Don't you think, Mister?
是啊
Yes.
現在你背部躺下來
You lie back down now.
我要替你包?腳
I'm gonna cover your legs up for you.
艾琳娜 我們可以停一會兒
Irena, we can stop for a while.
不用
No.
吸吮這個就好
just suck on this.
不! 拜託 不! 不!
No! Please, no! No!
噓 噓
來吧 我們必須繼續走
Come on. We've got to keep going.
我名字叫艾琳娜.吉琳斯卡
My name is Irena Zieilnska.
噓
我名字叫艾琳娜.吉琳斯卡
My name is Irena Zieilnska.
噓 噓 噓
把我放到地上 安德瑞斯
Put me on the ground, Andrejs.
把我放到地上就好
just lay me on the ground.
沒關係
It's okay.
請主你的天使來接她
Command thine angels to receive her
並帶她到天堂...
and to take her to heaven-
她的國度
her country.
阿門
Amen.
我真的喜歡這一個
I really like this one.
你何時畫的?
When did you do that?
在古拉格第二晚
Second night in the Gulag.
可憐的卡濟 腳總是有麻煩
Poor Kazik, always in trouble with his feet.
這是誰?
Who is this?
你
You.
看起來像我父親
Looks like my father.
那個是我現在的樣子嗎?
Is that how I look now?
不
No.
現在你看起來更糟
Now, you look worse.
你抓住她的笑容
You caught her smile.
看
Look.
這只是草圖
This is-just a sketch.
但我會繼續畫它
But I'll work on it.
我會畫它
I'll do it.
那真是傑出的工作
That's really fine work.
你是個很棒的藝術家 托馬斯
You're a great artist, Tomasz.
它幾乎就像一張相片
It's almost like a photography.
它是影像
It's the shadow.
它真的很漂亮
It's really nice.
我們必須到那些山丘
We have to get to those hills.
水可能收集在那裡
Water may be trapped there.
來吧 來吧 起來 起來
Come on. Come on, get up. Get up.
密斯特
Mister.
來吧
Come on.
留下我繼續走
Go on without me.
我完了
I'm done.
去吧
Go.
佐仁...
Zoran...
你到山丘找水
you go to the hills and look for water.
然後你在那裡等我們
And you wait for us there.
不
No.
去吧
Yes.
我們會趕上的
We'll catch up.
你找到水了嗎?
Did you find water?
沒有
No.
給我看
Show me.
拜託給我看
Please show me.
在哪裡?
Where-?
你在哪裡?
Where are you?
有...
There's-
水!
water!
佐仁
Zoran.
這附近
Around here.
看啊?
Look at that, uh?
要是它有毒呢? 我們怎麼吃它?
What if-if it's poisonous? How can we eat it?
不 不 不 我們砍掉它的頭
No, no, no, we cut off its head.
給我刀子
Here. Give me the knife.
啊 看一下
Ah, look at that.
吃起來像雞肉
Tastes like chicken.
對
Yeah.
一隻大又黑 有毒的無腳雞
A big, black, poisonous chicken with no legs.
嗯 不錯
Well, it's not bad.
你知道嗎 瓦卡談到彼此吃人
You know, Valka talked of eating each other
當我們在西伯利亞時
when we were in Siberia.
他有說?
He did?
對
Yes.
然後? 你會吃我嗎?
And? Would you have eaten me?
會
Yeah.
會 當然
Yeah, of course.
我永遠不會吃你
I would never have eaten you.
這個嘛 為何不會?
Well, why not?
太多筋和太苦了
Too stringy and bitter.
我寧可吃蛇
I'd rather eat snake.
這裡一些水
Here's some water.
它可能殺了你 記得嗎?
It can kill you, remember?
什麼?
What?
仁慈
Kindness.
靠泥漿和蛇 你能活多久?
How long can you survive on mud and snakes?
留我在這裡就好
Just leave me here.
你不能 對吧?
You can't, can you?
注意聽著 密斯特
Look, Mister-
什麼?
What?
你知道 我可能不知道你的名字
You know, I may not even know your first name,
但我 啊...
but I ...
我知道你兒子的名字
I know your son's name.
艾琳娜告訴你的?
Irena told you?
對
Yes.
我可以說他的名字嗎?
Can I say his name?
大衛
David.
說他的名字無法讓他起死回生
Saying his name won't bring him back.
你打算做的
What are you trying to do,
是給我活下去的意志嗎?
give me the will to live?
是那意思嗎?
Is that it?
叫我不要放棄?
Stop me from giving up?
而你正在放棄?
And are you giving up?
在集中營裡 有些人視死亡為自由
In the camps, some saw death as freedom.
那麼為何你不自殺就好?
Then why didn't you just kill yourseif?
生存是一種抗議
Survival was a kind of protest.
活著是我的懲罰
Being alive was my punishment.
懲罰什麼?
Punishment for what?
我帶大衛去蘇聯
I brought David to Russia.
現在沒人能原諒你
And now no one can forgive you.
你不能原諒你自己
And you can't forgive yourself.
艾琳娜告訴我...
Irena told me...
他們折磨你妻子...
that they tortured your wife...
而她告發你
and she informed on you.
對
Yes.
他們對我孩子做一樣的事
They did the same thing to my boy.
然後他們在他頭上開了一槍
Then they shot him in the head.
我妻子還活著
My wife is alive.
她活著...
She lived-
而且被釋放了 我知道就那麼多
and was released. That much I know.
但她永遠不能原諒她自己
But she'll never be able to forgive herseif
對於她所做的事
for what she's done.
你知道嗎 只有我能做那事
You see, only I can do that.
她會折磨她自己 就像你一樣
She will be torturing herself, just like you.
因此你明白 我必須回去
So you see, I have to get back.
我必須回去
I- have-to-get-back.
亞努思
Janusz.
打包你的東西 快
Pack your things, quick.
亞努思!
Janusz!
你聽到了嗎?
Do you hear that?
那是什麼?
What is that?
西藏
Tibet.
拉薩
Lhasa.
印度在哪裡?
And where is India?
嗯
印度
India.
印度 是啊
India. Yes.
翻過山有條鐵路到錫金
There is the track to Sikkim, over the mountains.
很多人去那裡
Many people go there.
路上有村莊嗎?
Are there villages on the way?
小村莊 有的
Small villages, yes.
他們會給你食物
They give you food.
生火用燃料
Fuel for fire.
但你們現在不能走
But you can't go now.
為什麼?
Why?
如果大雪來 很困難
If big snow comes, very difficult.
你們等到春天
You wait until spring.
這個家庭收留你們
This family keep you.
嗯 我們在冬天不能越過山
Well, we can't cross the mountains in winter.
他說很難 但不是不可能
He said it was difficult but not impossible.
亞努思 只有3個月
Janusz, it's only three months.
注意聽著 我們不能放鬆
Look, we can't let go.
你是什麼意思?
What do you mean?
如果我們現在停止 那麼我們就會屈服於疲憊
If we stop now, then we'll give In to exhaustion.
不 不是屈服
No, it's not giving in.
我們筋疲力盡了
We are exhausted.
我會睡到春天 就像熊在洞穴裡
I will sleep till spring like a bear in a cave.
你可以研究佛經並成為和尚
You can study Buddhism and become a monk.
但首先你必須學習如何喜歡他們的茶
But first you must learn how to like their tea.
我已經喜歡上茶了
I already like the tea.
晚安
Good night.
你呢 密斯特?
What about you, Mister?
3或4個月你打算做什麼?
What are you going to do for three or four months?
我要去拉薩
I'm going to Lhasa.
我們的朋友已經聯繫
Our friend has a contact.
他認為他能經由中國把我弄出去
He thinks he can get me out through China.
那裡有個美軍任務
There's a U.S. military mission there.
先為自己著想
Looking out for number one.
那不是你們美國人說的嗎?
Isn't that what you Americans say?
佐仁
Zoran-
Zoran.
什麼?
What?
我們逃脫了
We escaped.
我們做到了
We made it.
你說的對
You're right.
他說的對
He's right.
除了幾座山外 我們到了
Apart from a few mountains, we are there.
我們做到了
We made it.
不是我們全部人
Not all of us.
對 不是我們全部人
No, not all of us.
你打算做什麼 密斯特?
What are you going to do, Mister?
當你回到家時
When you go back home.
家?
Home?
建地鐵?
Build Metros?
可能觀望一陣子
Might drift a while.
我會抗戰
I will fight.
首先德國 然後蘇聯
First Germans, then Russians.
再然後呢?
And then?
重建你的教會?
Re-build your church?
不
No.
我會死於抗戰
I will die fighting.
我要把托馬斯作品拍照送去報紙
I'm going to get Tomasz' pictures to a newspaper
或讓他們以某種方式刊登
or get them published somehow.
然後我要煮他的雞
And then I'm going to cook his chicken
但要加額外的鹽 就是要煩他
but with extra salt, just-just to annoy him.
你呢 亞努思?
And you, Janusz?
只要共產黨在波蘭
As long as the communists are in Poland,
你不能回去
you cannot go back.
他們會射殺你的 亞努思
They'll shoot you, Janusz.
我只會 啊 繼續走 你知道的 直到結束
I'll just, uh-keep going, you know, until it's over.
我會繼續走
I'll just keep walking.
他走了
He's gone.
亞努思!
Janusz!
您好
Namaste.
歡迎來到印度
Welcome to India.
請拿出護照
Paper passport, please.
護照
Passport.
我們...我們...我們沒有
We-we-we don't have.
沒關係 跟我來
Never mind. Come with me.
你們來自哪裡?
Where have you come from?
西伯利亞
Siberia.
西伯利亞?
Siberia?
你們怎麼來的 先生?
And how did you come, sir?
我們走路
We walked.
走路?
Walked?
1945年5月8日 歐洲反法西斯戰爭勝利 (納粹德國無條件投降)
1945-1948年 蘇聯在波蘭 強迫施行共產主義
東歐籠罩鐵幕之下
1956年 匈牙利起義 (因鎮壓而結束)
1961年 柏林圍牆建立
1968年 蘇聯派兵進入布拉格
1980年 波蘭團結運動聯盟 挑戰共產主義
1989年 共產主義崩潰瓦解 (柏林圍牆亦於同年倒塌)
波蘭自由